<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://alshedivat.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://alshedivat.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-08-11T22:00:30+00:00</updated><id>https://alshedivat.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Welcome!</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Hosting my first website</title><link href="https://alshedivat.github.io/blog/2024/Jekyll-Website/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hosting my first website"/><published>2024-08-11T16:10:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-11T16:10:00+00:00</updated><id>https://alshedivat.github.io/blog/2024/Jekyll-Website</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alshedivat.github.io/blog/2024/Jekyll-Website/"><![CDATA[<p>When I first decided to create my own personal website, I was faced with a common dilemma: which platform should I use? The obvious choice seemed to be website builders like Wix, Squarespace, and Weebly given there simplicity and popularity. However, as I explored my options, I found myself drawn to something more customizable and developer-friendly…. Jekyll.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="why-jekyll">Why Jekyll?</h2> <p>One of the main reasons to I chose Jekyll is the unparalleled flexibility it offers. Unlike Wordpress, which can sometimes feel restrictive with its themes and plugins, Jekyll gives me complete control over every aspect of my website. From the layout and design to the functionality and content structure, I can tailor anything to match my vision if I wanted to do so. This level of customization was exactly what I was looking for as someone who enjoys tinkering and learning new things with code and experimenting with different ideas.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="integration-with-github-pages">Integration with GitHub Pages</h2> <p>Another significant advantage of Jekyll is its seamless integration with <strong>Github Pages</strong>. As someone who loves exploring projects on GitHub, I was excited to use a platform that works so well with Git’s version control system. With Jekyll, I can host my website directly from a GitHub repository, making it easy to manage updates, track changes, and collaborate with others if needed. Plus, deploying the site is as simple as pushing commits to my repository—no need to worry about complex setups or hosting fees.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Jekyll"/><category term="self-hosting"/><category term="tutorial"/><category term="website"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Learning how to set up and host my own website]]></summary></entry></feed>